Guide to the Mina Loy Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mina Loy papers
1914-1960
YCAL MSS 6
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.25
(8 boxes)
The papers contain prose, poetry, drawings, and designs documenting the artistic career of modernist poet and artist Mina Loy.
Loy, Mina
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Papers were donated to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library by Loy's daughter, Joella Haweis Bayer, in 1974 and 1975.
Associated Materials
Carolyn Burke Collection on Mina Loy and Lee Miller (YCAL MSS 778). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 8: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
MINA LOY (1882-1966)
Mina Loy, the modernist poet, painter, playwright, actress, and designer of lampshades, lived in Europe during the height of the Futurist, Dada, and Surrealist movements. Her talent, intellect, and exceptional beauty made her one of the central figures of the literary and artistic avant garde who later gathered around Alfred Stieglitz, Walter Conrad Arensberg, and Alfred Kreymborg in New York. Although Loy was a multi-gifted woman, her fame largely rests with her poetry, which is daring in its technical experimentation and feminist in its exploration of female oppression. Two collections of her poems were published during her lifetime, Lunar Baedecker (Paris: Contact Editions, 1923) and Lunar Baedeker & Time-Tables (Highlands, N.C.: Jargon, 1958); another collection, The Last Lunar Baedeker (Highlands, N.C.: Jargon, 1982), appeared posthumously.
Mina Loy, the eldest daughter of Sigmund and Julian Bryan Lowy, was born in London on December 27, 1882. She went to Munich in 1899 to study art with Angelo Jank and during this time shortened her name from Mina Gertrude Lowy to Mina Loy. In 1901-1902 she studied painting in England with Augustus John and met Stephen Haweis, whom she married in Paris on December 31, 1903. The couple lived and painted in Paris for the next three years and frequented the salon of Gertrude Stein. They moved to Florence in 1906, but their marriage collapsed in 1913 and Haweis left for Australia and the South Seas. At about the same time Loy probably had affairs with Filippo Marinetti and Giovanni Papini and her poetry, which reflected her interest in the Futurists, first began to appear in print. Loy came to New York in 1916, worked in a lampshade studio, acted in the Provincetown Theatre, and associated with the poets who published in Others. In New York City she met Arthur Cravan, whom she married in Mexico City in 1918 after obtaining a divorce from Haweis. Soon thereafter Cravan disappeared in Mexico and his body was later found in the desert.
When Loy returned to Paris in 1923, Robert McAlmon published Lunar Baedecker, which assured her a place among such modernist contemporary writers as Marianne Moore, Williams Carlos Williams, and T. S. Eliot. As the widow of poet-boxer Cravan, she maintained contact with the Dadaists and Surrealists, who saw Cravan as a hero. She continued her friendships with Marcel Duchamp, Gertrude Stein, Djuna Barnes and her agent Carl Van Vechten, and met many of the expatriates residing in Paris, including James Joyce and Constantin Brancusi. Although her literary career was at its height, she continued to support her family through the design and manufacture of lampshades for the shop that she opened with the financial backing of Peggy Guggenheim. "Anglo-Mongrels and the Rose," a semi-autobiographical poem about Loy's Victorian upbringing, was published in two issues of the Little Review (1923) and in McAlmon's The Contact Collection of Contemporary Writers (1925). She also wrote several parallel autobiographical prose narratives on the same theme that were never published. Loy continued to paint in the 1930s, exhibiting her monochrome sand paintings in New York, and worked on another unpublished novel, "Insel."
In 1936 she moved to New York City where she remained for nearly twenty years, writing poetry and creating collages out of materials she found in back alleys and trash cans. In 1958 her poetry was republished in Lunar Baedeker & Time-Tables; the following year she received the Copley Foundation Award for Outstanding Achievement in Art and exhibited her "Constructions" at the Bodley Gallery. She died in Aspen, Colorado on September 29, 1966 after a short illness.
Loy had three children by her first husband and one by her second: Oda Janet Haweis (1903-1904), who died in infancy; Joella Synara Haweis Levy Bayer (1907- ); John Giles Stephen Musgrove Haweis (1909-1923); and Jemima Fabienne Cravan Benedict (1919- ).
Sources: Burke, Carolyn, "Mina Loy," in Dictionary of Literary Biography (Detroit: Gale, 1980), 4:259-60; Kouidis, Virginia M., Mina Loy, American Modernist Poet (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1980); Loy, Mina, The Last Lunar Baedeker, ed. Roger L. Conover (Highlands, N.C.: Jargon, 1982).
Scope and Contents
The Mina Loy Papers contain prose, poetry, drawings, designs, and copyright inventions documenting the life of modernist poet and artist Mina Loy. The papers span the dates 1914-1960.
Series I, Writings, begins with four boxes of drafts of six unpublished autobiographical novels based upon Loy's childhood in England, her student days in Germany, and her literary and art career in France and Italy. The novels are alphabetically arranged by title and their subject matter often overlaps.
Loy's childhood is the subject of three of the novels: "Goy Israels," "The Child and the Parent," and "Islands in the Air." Composed largely of fragments, "Goy Israels" probably represented Loy's first attempt to write about her stormy relationship with her family and her art school days in England. Loy, as the principal character "Goy Israels," discusses love, sex, marriage, and her Jewish identity. "The Child and the Parent," a title supplied from a fragment in the papers (Box 1, folder 10), may be an early version of "Islands in the Air." It covers Loy's life from childhood through marriage and motherhood. "Islands" ends with Loy's student days in Munich. The protagonists are "Ada" in "The Child" and "Linda" in "Islands," yet many of the chapters have similar titles and content, such as "Arrival on the Scene of an Accident" in "The Child" and "Accident" in "Islands" (Box 1, folder 12 and Box 4, folder 61). The oppression of women is the subject of chapter nine in both books.
"Esau Penfold," an unfinished work, is probably based upon Loy's early days in Florence with Haweis. In the second chapter, "Esau" and "Ova," the two primary characters, meet "Geronimo," a Futurist like Papini. Three caricatures accompany the novel and may be of Haweis.
Loy's subsequent affairs with Marinetti and Papini provide the focus of "Brontolivido," a novel set in Italy that portrays the two "Flabbergusts," "Brontolivido" and "Johannes," and their relationship with "Jemima." The material is arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
The last novel, "Insel," is loosely based upon Loy's friendship with the Surrealist painter and drug addict, Richard Oelze, during the 1930s in Paris and may have been written as a continuation of "Islands in the Air." It would logically follow "Colossus," a work about Loy's travels in Mexico with Cravan, which is not found in the papers.
Loy's poetry is housed in Box 5 and is divided into drafts published in The Last Lunar Baedeker and other drafts not included in The Last Lunar Baedeker. The poems are arranged by title and were primarily written in the 1940s. Many poems are about the United States, which she became a citizen of in 1946, including "American * a Miracle" and "Hot Cross Bum," about the "blowsy angels" who were her derelict neighbors in the Bowery from 1949-53. Some of Loy's headings are different from the published version: "There Is No Love Alone," for instance, is entitled "Amor" on the manuscript. Many poems are also annotated with pencil sketches.
Some of the most significant other poems are "Biography of Songge Byrd," about Isadora Duncan (Box 5, folder 130) and "Esau Penfold," a free verse biography of Stephen Haweis. She also wrote a prose version of "I Almost Saw God in the Metro" entitled "A Hard Luck Story" (Box 6, folder 157). The poetry section includes reviews of Lunar Baedecker by Harriet Monroe and Yvor Winters, who described Loy's poems as "images that have frozen into epigrams." ( Dial, 1926).
The series of Loy's Writings is completed in Box 6 with a collection of her shorter works, most of which were not published during her lifetime, except for "Aphorisms on Futurism" ( Camera Work, 1914) and a play that mocks insincere disciples of art called "The Pamperers" ( Dial, 1920). "Sacred Prostitute," an experimental play, satirizes the Futurist male attitudes toward women. Another parody, "Pazzerella," is a spoof of Papini's work. Her short stories are often autobiographical: "Hush Money," for example, is about the death of her father. The essays reflect her longstanding interest in religion, literature, and art. "Phenomenon in American Art," for instance, is about Joseph Cornell, an artist friend from New York. The collection also contains some early attempts at fairy tales, such as "Crocodile Without Any Tail" and even a ballet, "Crystal Pantomime."
Series II, Other Papers, housed in Box 7, contains drawings and notes. Her drawings include fashion designs, a collage, and more than a dozen unidentified portraits in pencil and wash. A collection of copyright inventions include a corselet or armour for the body to correct "middle-age figure curvature," a stage set for the lyrical line "coloured folk have the moon in their eyes," and a valentine that ticks. There is one lampshade design decorated with an airplane.
Five folders of notes complete the papers. On Jews she wrote, "When the gentile world required a Saviour they nailed up the Christ, when it required a second Saviour to counteract the effects of the first, Freud was at its service." As might be expected, her other subjects include metaphysics, literature, and observations on artists such as "the aesthetic acrobat, Picasso."
Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Feminism; Futurism (Art); Futurism (Literary movement); Jewish way of life; Poetry, Modern -- 20th Century; Women; Autobiographies; Drawings; Poems; Artists -- United States; Authors; Haweis, Stephen; Loy, Mina; Marinetti, F. T., 1876-1944; Oelze, Richard, 1900-1980; Papini, Giovanni, 1881-1956
- Writings, 1914-60; Series I; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Boxes 1-6 hold Series I, Writings, which is divided into three sections, Novels, Poetry, and Shorter Works. The first section, Novels, is arranged alphabetically by title, and material within each title has been placed in the following order: notes, drafts, and fragments. Poetry, in the second section, is divided into drafts published in The Last Lunar Baedeker and other drafts. A folder of printed reviews completes the division. The third section, Shorter Works, is arranged alphabetically by title followed by unidentified fragments. A few manuscripts of verse and prose are filed in Box 7 because of their size.
  - NOVELS
    - "Brontolivido"
      - "Absolution": draft (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "First Costa Visit": draft, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Gloria": draft, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "Illicit Honeymoon": draft (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - [Marinetti]: draft of a dialogue, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - [Papini]: notes on Johannes and Geronimo (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Rome": draft fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Second Costa Visit": draft fragments (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Vallombrosa": draft, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The Child and the Parent"
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "The Child": drafts of chapters III-VI, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
      - "The Parent": drafts of chapters VII-XII, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15-20)
    - "Esau Penfold"
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Chapter I: draft fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Chapter II: draft, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
      - Illustrations, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "Goy Israels"
      - Draft: incomplete, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Insel"
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - First draft, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 32-35)
      - First draft: fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36-39)
      - Second draft: copies 1-3 (Box 3, Folder 40-48)
      - Second draft: variants (Box 3, Folder 49-50)
      - Third draft: copies 1-2, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51-56)
      - Third draft: transcript of pp. 88-92, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "Islands in the Air"
      - Chapters I-X: drafts, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 58-69)
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 70-71)
  - POETRY
    - Drafts for The Last Lunar Baedeker
      - Lists of poem titles, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - "Aid of the Madonna", 1943 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - "America _ a Miracle", 1941 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - "Anglo-Mongrels and the Rose": fragment (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - "Apology of Genius II", 1930 October 28 (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - "Aviators' Eyes", 1943 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - "Birth of Melody", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - "The Black Virginity": photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - "Brain", 1945 Aug (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - "Breath Bank", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - "Brilliant Confusion of Brilliance", 1945 Sep (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - "Ceiling at Dawn", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 83)
      - "Chiffon Velours", 1944 May 6 (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - "Child Chanting", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 85)
      - "Continuity", 1943 (Box 5, Folder 86)
      - "Descent of the Ganges", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 87)
      - "Echo", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 88)
      - "Ephemerid", 1944 Aug (Box 5, Folder 89)
      - "Evolution", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 90)
      - "Faun-Fare", 1948 Dec 27 (Box 5, Folder 91)
      - "Hilarious Israel", 1944 Dec 1 (Box 5, Folder 92)
      - "Hot Cross Bum", 1949 Aug 30 (Box 5, Folder 93)
      - "I Almost Saw God in the Metro", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 94)
        Related Archival Materials note
        See also: "A Hard Luck Story" Box 6, folder 157
      - "Idiot Child on a Fire-Escape", 1943 (Box 5, Folder 95)
      - "Impossible Opus", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 96)
      - "L'Inavouable Enfant", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 97)
      - "Joyce's Ulysses": fragment, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 98)
      - "Jules Pascin", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 99)
      - "Lady Laura in Bohemia," fragment, 1925 Aug 2 (Box 5, Folder 99a)
      - "Letters of the Unliving", 1949 Jun 19 (Box 5, Folder 100)
      - "Maiden Song", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 101)
      - "Mass Production on 14th Street", 1942 Jul 27 (Box 5, Folder 102)
      - "The Mediterranean Sea", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 103)
      - "Mexican Desert" (Box 5, Folder 104)
      - "Moreover the Moon", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 105)
      - "Mother Earth", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 106)
      - "Nancy Cunard", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 107)
      - "Negro Dancer", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 108)
      - "O Hell", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 109)
      - "An Old Woman", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 110)
      - "Omen of Victory", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 111)
      - "On Third Avenue", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 112)
      - "Overnight", 1943 (Box 5, Folder 113)
      - "Photo After Pogrom", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 114)
      - "Portrait of a Nun", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 115)
      - "Property of Pigeons", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 116)
      - "Repassed Platform", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 117)
      - "Revelation", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 118)
      - "Show Me a Saint Who Suffered", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 119)
      - "The Song of the Nightingale Is Like the Scent of Syringe": fragment, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 120)
      - "Songge Byrd", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 121)
        See also: "Biography of Songge Byrd," Box 5, folder 130
      - "Stravinski's Flute", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 122)
      - "Summer Night in a Florentine Slum", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 123)
      - "There Is No Love Alone", 1949 Jan 29 (Box 5, Folder 124)
      - "Time Bomb", n.y. Aug 31 (Box 5, Folder 125)
      - "Transformation Scene", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 126)
      - "Vision on Broadway", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 127)
      - "White Petunia", 1944 Jul (Box 5, Folder 128)
      - Reviews, 1923, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Other drafts
      - "Biography of Songge Byrd", 1952 (Box 5, Folder 130)
      - "Crowd", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 131)
      - "Early Botany", 1943 May 11 (Box 5, Folder 132)
      - "Electric Love Release": fragment, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 133)
      - "Esau Penfold", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134)
        See also: Esau Penfold, Box 1, folders 21-26
      - "Film Face", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 135)
      - "In Extremis", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 136)
      - "Indelicate Light" (Box 5, Folder 137)
      - "The Infinite Is the Obvious", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 138)
      - "Interplay", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 139)
      - "Intimate", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 140)
      - "Jesus and Eros" (Box 5, Folder 141)
      - "Let Us Pray", 1942 Oct (Box 5, Folder 142)
      - "Marble", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 143)
      - "Passivia", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 144)
      - "Pygmaleon and Galatea" (Box 5, Folder 145)
      - "Silence", 1943 (Box 5, Folder 146)
      - "Soldier", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 147)
      - "Surfeit of Controversy", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
      - Unidentified fragments, 1925-30,n.d. (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - "The Agony of the Partition", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - "All the Laughs in One Short Story by MacAlmon": fragment, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - "Aphorisms on Futurism", [1914] (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - "Bye-Thoughts", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 152a)
    - "Conversion", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 153)
    - "The Crocodile without Any Tail", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - "Crystal Pantomime (Ballet)", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - "Gertrude Stein", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 156)
    - "A Hard Luck Story": drafts and fragments (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - "History of Religion and Eros": notes and drafts (Box 6, Folder 158-59)
    - "Hush Money", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - "In Maine Greens Colony", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - "Incident", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - "Lady Asterisk", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - "Mabel", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - "The Metaphysical Pattern in Aesthetics", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - "Mi and Lo" (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - "Monde Triple-Extra": fragment (Box 6, Folder 167)
    - "The Oil in the Machine?", 1921 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - "The Pamperers": fragment, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - "Pazzerella", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 170-71)
    - "Phenomenon in American Art", 1950 Nov 25 (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - "Piero and Eliza" (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - "Preceptors of Childhood", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - "Rosa", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - "Sacred Prostitute", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - "Static", 1944 (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - "The Stomach", 1921 Jul (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - "The Three Wishes", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - "Transfiguration": fragment, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 180)
    - "Tuning in on the Atom Bomb", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 181)
    - "Universal Food Machine", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 182)
    - Unidentified fragments, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 183)
- Other Papers, 1940-60; Series II; 1.5; (1 box)
  Box 7 holds Series II, Other Papers, which is divided into two sections, Drawings and Designs and Notes.
  - DRAWINGS AND DESIGNS
    - Designs, 1941, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - Figure drawings, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - Inventions, 1940-60 (Box 7, Folder 186)
  - NOTES
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 187)
    - On Art, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - On Jews, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - On Literature, 1948, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - On Metaphysics, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 191)
    - [Empty folders] (Box 7, Folder 192-194)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.25; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  Arrangement
  The material is arranged in folder order.
  - Box 1, folders 7, 22, 25 (Box 8, Folder 195-97)
  - Box 4, folder 71 (Box 8, Folder 198)
  - Box 5, folder 74 (Box 8, Folder 199)
  - Box 6, folder 180 (Box 8, Folder 200)
  - Box 7, folder 187 (Box 8, Folder 201)